{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Peace in this region was the subject of the Sunningdale Agreement, which failed after bombings perpetrated by the Glenanne Gang. The Shankill Butchers were active in this region. A group from this region carried out a terrorist attack at the Brighton Hotel that failed to kill Margaret Thatcher. Senator George Mitchell developed principles for peace in this region that were adopted in the Good Friday Agreement. For ten points, name this island that was home to Catholic and Protestant violence during the Troubles.",
      "answer": [
        "Ireland",
        "Northern Ireland before “island” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a court case involving this state, William Wirt was hired by a Native American tribe that was declared a “domestic dependent nation.” A 1972 case involving this state started a nationwide moratorium on the death penalty; another case four years later, also involving this state, ended it. The Furman and Gregg cases involved this state, which arrested a white missionary for attempting to aid the Cherokee Nation, leading to an 1832 Supreme Court case. For ten points, name this US state involved in the Worcester case.",
      "answer": "Georgia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This gospel is the only one where Jesus tries to keep his identity secret, and its manuscripts either have a “longer” ending or a “lost” shorter ending. Augustine thought this book was abridged from a longer gospel, but scholars now believe it was a source for the other synoptics. In this book, Jesus says “the Sabbath was made for man, not man for the sabbath.” For ten points, name this shortest and earliest gospel, the second book of the New Testament.",
      "answer": "the Gospel/Book of Mark"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rogier Verbeek wrote a journal analyzing this event, which was the subject of a BBC documentary subtitled The Last Days. The sun appeared blue and green after the rise of aerosols following this event, which killed over 36,000 people. Though it occurred over 4,000 kilometers away, inhabitants of Rodrigues Island were able to hear this event, which caused the global temperature to fall by over 2 degrees Fahrenheit. For ten points, name this massive 1883 volcanic eruption on an Indonesian island.",
      "answer": "eruption of Krakatoa"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rebecca Walker’s article denouncing this man introduced “third-wave feminism.” A New York Times advertisement attacking this man featured 1600 female signatures. This man refused to take a polygraph test, unlike his accuser, who worked with him at the EEOC. This man described his situation as a “high-tech lynching for uppity Blacks” at his nomination hearing in October 1991. For ten points, name this man who was confirmed to the Supreme Court despite allegations that he sexually harassed Anita Hill.",
      "answer": "Clarence Thomas"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man declared he would not sacrifice “a frog’s hind legs” for the social experiment that his home country was conducting. The Institute of Experimental Medicine’s Physiology wing was first headed by this man, who studied transmarginal inhibition, an organism’s response to stress. He implanted permanent fistulas in test subjects to measure saliva levels, laying the groundwork for his research in classical conditioning. For ten points, name this Russian psychologist who probably did not ring an actual bell to make his dogs drool.",
      "answer": "Ivan Pavlov"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country fought the Duar War with Britain, and this country was united by a religious figure known as the Shabdrung. This country enforces the traditional gho robe on its Hindu minority, and this country transitioned to democracy in 2005 under its king, Jigme Singye. This country is supported by India in several border disputes against China. For ten points, name this Himalayan kingdom led by the Whangchuck Dynasty from Thimphu.",
      "answer": "Bhutan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s residents included Dorothy Talbye, who was hanged for murdering her three-year-old daughter despite being insane. This city was originally named for the Naumkeag people at its founding in 1629; a year later, a small fleet led by the Arbella landed at this settlement, bringing Simon and Anne Bradstreet to the Americas. John Winthrop’s Puritans fueled the early growth of this city, where Betty Parris, Abigail Williams, and other young girls caused a panic in 1692. For ten points, name this colonial Massachusetts town where 19 people were executed on suspicion of witchcraft.",
      "answer": "Salem"
    },
    {
      "question": "William Graves led an US expedition that occupied this port city on its way to attempt to rescue the Czech Legion. This port city was known as Haishenwai before its transfer in the Treaty of Aigun. The city of Novosibirsk was founded in 1893 along a railway that ended in this city. For ten points, name this port city whose name means “Ruler of the East,” the Eastern terminus of the Trans-Siberian Railway.",
      "answer": "Vladivostok"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Duke of this region fought a civil war with the Armagnac branch of a royal family. The League of the Public Weal was established by a duke of this region; another duke of this region assassinated Louis, the duke of Orleans, in 1410. This region was led by Charles the Bold and Philip the Good, and troops from this region captured Joan of Arc. For ten points, name this region of eastern France, a powerful grand duchy in the late medieval period.",
      "answer": [
        "Burgundy",
        "Bourgogne"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "“Hill of Sacrifice” is the translation of the native name of this island’s Punchbowl Crater, which today houses a military cemetery. A mountain on this island was named by British sailors who found calcite crystals nearby. The Resolution visited this island’s Waimea Bay shortly after the death of James Cook on a nearby island. Kamehameha III built a still-extant palace on this island in 1845. Diamond Head overlooks Waikiki Beach in Honolulu on, for ten points, what most populous Hawaiian island?",
        "answer": "Oahu do not"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Father Damien spent sixteen years engaged in charitable and missionary work on this other Hawaiian island, which was home to a leper colony for over 100 years beginning in the 1860s.",
        "answer": "Molokai"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a diary written from this location, one man described how his eyes “started out from their Orbits like a Rabbit’s.” Albigence Waldo was a surgeon at this location, whose inhabitants had previously been defeated at the Battle of White Marsh. The “Blue Book” was circulated at this location by a man who had previously served the King of Prussia. Over 2,000 men died in this location outside Philadelphia in one season. For ten points, name this location where George Washington’s troops spent a winter during the American Revolution.",
        "answer": "Valley Forge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Prussian officer and baron drilled the American troops at Valley Forge.",
        "answer": "Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When advocates for this cause marched on Parliament in 1910, the ensuing police brutality led it to be known as Black Friday. A supporter of this cause took a meat cleaver to Velasquez’s Rokeby Venus a day after another supporter had been arrested. After supporters of this movement were targeted by the Cat and Mouse act, a supporter of this movement was killed after jumping in front of a horse at the 1913 Epsom Derby. Mary Richardson and Emily Davison were Englishwomen who fought for, for ten points, what expansion of political rights?",
        "answer": [
          "women’s suffrage",
          "equivalent answers related to voting rights for women in the UK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the numerous arrests of this suffragette inspired Mary Richardson’s slashing of the Rokeby Venus. This woman broke with her activist daughters Sylvia and Adela, who disagreed with her tactics.",
        "answer": "Emmeline Pankhurst"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Mark Fisher wrote about the idea that this system is inescapable in his book on this sort of “Realism.” Another thinker wrote that Calvinism was related to the rise of this system in his book on The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of this concept. Some people argue for a laissez-faire approach to this system, which advances a “free market” economy. For ten points, name this economic system which allows private ownership of the means of production.",
        "answer": [
          "capitalism",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism was written by this German social theorist.",
        "answer": "Maximilian Karl Emil Weber"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Indigenoussoldierswhofoughtforcolonizingforcesinthiscountrywereknownaslascarins.Portuguese expansion in this country was stopped when one army was annihilated in the Campaign of Danture. The Temple of the Tooth was built in the capital of this island’s Kingdom of Kandy. Under British imperial rule, this island was known as Ceylon. For ten points, name this island where the Portuguese founded a trading station called Colombo, south of India.",
        "answer": "Sri Lanka"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Kingdom of Kandy fought a series of wars against Portugal named after this ethnic group that made up the kingdom. It makes up the majority of Sri Lanka’s population today.",
        "answer": "Sinhalese"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a novel by this author, the doctor William Bradshaw recommends that a veteran adjust his “proportion.” In the second section of a novel by this author, “Time Passes,” Prue dies in childbirth while Andrew is killed during World War I. This woman wrote a novel in which Septimus Smith suffers from shell shock before he commits suicide by jumping out of an apartment window. For ten points, name this author of To the Lighthouse and Mrs. Dalloway.",
        "answer": "Virginia Woolf"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Woolf was a member of this circle of intellectuals, including John Maynard Keynes and Clive Bell, which was named for the district in London’s West End where they gathered.",
        "answer": "Bloomsbury Group"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A rebel against this country’s colonial governments used the nom de guerre Abel Djassi and founded the PAIGC. This country fought anticolonial movements led by Holden Roberto and Samora Machel, and it used the Pink Map to promote its colonial claims. This country’s colonists promoted the ideology of Lusotropicalism, but its colonization of Africa ended in 1975 after the Carnation Revolution. For ten points, name this former colonial controller of Angola and Mozambique.",
        "answer": "Portugal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Carnation Revolution ended this Portuguese regime, which was led for 36 years by Antonio Salazar.",
        "answer": [
          "Estado Novo",
          "New State",
          "Second Republic"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was exacerbated after watchman Matthias Schaffer misdirected government services in the wrong direction. Daniel Sullivan may have started this event while attempting to steal from a household on 137 DeKoven Street. Renovations in the aftermath of this event allowed the city to host the 1893 World’s Fair. An Irishwoman was blamed for this event because her cow supposedly knocked over a lantern. For ten points, name this 1871 catastrophe that killed hundreds of people and destroyed thousands of buildings in Illinois.",
        "answer": "Great Chicago Fire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Great Chicago Fire did start in this Irishwoman’s farmhouse, but the legend of her cow knocking over the lantern was invented by a reporter.",
        "answer": "Catherine O’Leary"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Ronald Reagan",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Incumbent president defeated by Reagan in the 1980 election. He oversaw the Iran Hostage Crisis.",
          "answer": "James Earl “Jimmy” Carter Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Statewide political post held by Reagan, Jerry Brown, and Arnold Schwarzenegger.",
          "answer": "Governor of California"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet leader who Reagan implored to “tear down this wall” in a speech in Berlin.",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Minnesota senator who Reagan defeated in the 1984 presidential election.",
          "answer": "Walter Mondale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Three word slogan coined by Nancy Reagan to crack down on recreational drug use.",
          "answer": "Just Say No"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who attempted to charm Jodie Foster by assassinating Reagan in 1981.",
          "answer": "John Hinckley, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Speech given by Reagan at the 1964 RNC to support Barry Goldwater.",
          "answer": "A Time for Choosing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mississippi county where Reagan gave a controversial campaign speech in 1980, stating “I believe in states’ rights.”",
          "answer": "Neshoba County"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century European Politicians",
      "prompt": "Name the politician who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founded the Republic of Turkey after World War I and gave himself a name meaning “father of the Turks”.",
          "answer": [
            "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Became the first president of post-Soviet Russia after standing on a tank to deliver a speech during a coup attempt.",
          "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established a Nazi puppet government in World War II-era Norway, where his name now means traitor.",
          "answer": "Vidkun Quisling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founded the Solidarity movement and became the first president of post-Communist Poland.",
          "answer": "Lech Walesa , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ordered the sinking of the Rainbow Warrior and was the first Socialist elected President of France.",
          "answer": "Franc¸ois Mitterrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Issued a 1917 declaration calling for the establishment of a Jewish state on behalf of the British foreign office.",
          "answer": [
            "Arthur Balfour",
            "Balfour Declaration"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the Velvet Revolution in Czechoslovakia and was the first President of the Czech Republic.",
          "answer": "Vaclav Havel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as Viceroy of India from 1899 to 1905 and names a boundary line between Poland and modern Belarus",
          "answer": [
            "George Curzon",
            "Curzon Line"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Caribbean",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US territory struck by Hurricane Maria whose capital of San Juan is led by Carmen Yulin Cruz.",
          "answer": "Puerto Rico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Kingston was founded by survivors of the Port Royal earthquake.",
          "answer": "Jamaica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island country with capital of Nassau that gained independence from Britain in 1973.",
          "answer": "the Bahamas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prominent offshore tax haven, a British territory where the 1794 Wreck of the Ten Sail occurred.",
          "answer": "Cayman Islands"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dutch territory with capital at Oranjestad [oran-yeh-stahd] that abandoned plans for independence in the 1990s.",
          "answer": "Aruba"
        },
        {
          "question": "“C” of the ABC Islands, where a 1969 riot in Willemstad started with a strike by Dutch Shell oil workers.",
          "answer": "Cura¸cao"
        },
        {
          "question": "British territory that was nearly completely destroyed by a volcanic eruption in 1995.",
          "answer": "Montserrat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Alexander Hamilton was born.",
          "answer": "Nevis do not"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One artist from this country created collaged images he called prouns. A spiraling monument that was proposed, but never built, in this country was nicknamed “Tatlin’s Tower.” This home country of El Lissitzky persecuted the painter of (20 pts)",
        "Black Square and White on White in the 1920s. The sculpture “worker and (10 pts)",
        "peasant unite” was built by an artist from this country, Vera Mukhina. For ten points, name this country in which art was dominated by the “Socialist Realist” style and often depicted its dictator, Joseph Stalin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union or USSR",
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "CCCP",
        "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man lost a battle along the Enipeus River after Titus Labienus’s cavalry were shocked by infantry with pikes. After Cicero gave the speech Pro Lege Manilia, this man replaced Lucius Lucullus as commander in the (20 pts)",
        "Mithridatic Wars. The Lex Gabinia gave this man power to put down Cilician piracy in the Mediterranean. Ptolemy XIII ordered the death of this (10 pts)",
        "Roman in Egypt after he lost at the Battle of Pharsalus. For ten points, the First Triumvirate was composed of Marcus Crassus, Julius Caesar, and which man?"
      ],
      "answer": "Pompey the Great"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer wrote a Dervish chorus and a Turkish march for The Ruins of Athens, a selection of music to accompany a play written by German diplomat August von Kotzebue. The first opera played in post-war Berlin was a 1945 performance of this composer’s only opera, (20 pts)",
        "Fidelio. In 1989 at the Berlin Wall, Leonard Bernstein directed a modified version of this composer’s (10 pts)",
        "Choral Symphony. For ten points, name this German composer who used the “Ode to Joy” in his ninth and final symphony."
      ],
      "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man forced the surrender of William Hull by repeatedly marching his troops through the woods to create the impression of bigger numbers. This man allegedly proclaimed “now here is a man!” after meeting Isaac Brock. This man’s forces swelled after the (20 pts)",
        "New Madrid [MA-drid] earthquake was interpreted as an omen. Two years after this man’s brother, (10 pts)",
        "known as “the Prophet,” was defeated at Tippecanoe, this man was killed at the Battle of the Thames. For ten points, name this Shawnee chief who led a namesake confederacy in support of the British during the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": "Tecumseh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Soon after its establishment, this dynasty was ruled by a set of regents called the Oboi. The Revolt of the Three Feudatories targeted this dynasty, and one ruler of this dynasty was advised by the (20 pts)",
        "Jesuit Matteo Ricci. The Aisin Gioro were this dynasty’s ruling clan, and this dynasty, the target of the (10 pts)",
        "Taiping Rebellion, produced emperors such as Qianlong and Kangxi. For ten points, name this dynasty established by the Manchu people, the successors of the Ming."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Qing Dynasty",
        "Manchu before mention"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man allegedly commented “they shoot like pigs” after surviving a machine gun ambush that served as the basis for Frederick Forsyth’s The Day of the Jackal. This man’s car drove away despite two punctured (20 pts)",
        "tires in that assassination attempt. The OAS, which opposed this man’s signing of the (10 pts)",
        "Evian Accords, plotted that 1962 assassination attempt, for which Jean Bastien-Thiry was killed by the last firing squad in France. For ten points, name this founder of the Fifth Republic and leader of Free France."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2017, a party leadership election in this country was to include a businessman who refers to himself as “Mr. Wonderful” and appears on Shark Tank, but Kevin O’Leary dropped out a month before the vote. This country’s leader is under investigation for a potential conflict of interest after he went on a trip to (20 pts)",
        "Aga Khan IV’s private island. When asked why this country’s cabinet had gender equality, this country’s leader responded (10 pts)",
        "“because it’s 2015.” Stephen Harper resigned as leader of the Conservative Party in October 2015 in, for ten points, what country whose Prime Minister is Justin Trudeau?"
      ],
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of this group attained her nickname for the sound she made when pinched by George Spahn; that member, “Squeaky” Fromme, conducted a failed assassination attempt on Gerald Ford. (20 pts)",
        "Roman Polanski was filming in Europe when his wife was killed by members of this group, whose leader believed in the coming of a race war called (10 pts)",
        "“Helter Skelter.” This group was formed after its leader moved to San Francisco during the Summer of Love. For ten points, name this criminal “family” whose members killed Sharon Tate and several other people."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Manson family",
        "the Mansons"
      ]
    }
  ]
}